A Guide to the British Abolition Movement Papers 1821-1887
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
British Abolition Movement Papers 1821-1887
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3846
60 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Stuart W. Jackson of Gloucester, Virginia
Scope and Content Information
The papers contain documents, letters, broadsides and miscellaneous material relating to the abolition of the slave trade and the anti-slavery movement in Great Britain and America. A few of the letters were kept by the compiler for their autograph value (Duke of Wellington, Disraeli) but have no discernible connection to the abolition movement.
Correspondence and documents relate to the anti-slavery movement in America and to the abolition of slavery in Africa and South America, 1821-1887.
Much of the correspondence consists of letters written to Thomas Denman, Margaret Denman Cropper, and Henry William Macaulay on English efforts to abolish the international slave trade.
Of interest are letters from Sierra Leone residents seeking employment or making other requests of Henry William Macaulay or William Wilberforce.
Items of United States interest include a letter from Thomas Clarkson on slave-holding clergy in the South and letters from Frederick Douglass to Margaret Cropper on the anti-slavery cause, the aid of the Liverpool Society, gifts from Mrs. Cropper, and the destitution of escaped slaves.
There are also a few letters from Thomas Babington Macaulay to Mrs. Henry William Macaulay on family matters and a request for documents from the 1690s.
Miscellaneous letters include one from a gunner on the "Scylla," captured and imprisoned by the Carlists, and one from Robert Cecil on winning over the Roman Catholics of Ireland.
The papers also contain a few letters collected by the compiler for their autograph value and having nothing to do with abolition. These include two letters from the Duke of Wellington on a railway from Warrington to Liverpool, social notes from Disraeli and Bulwer-Lytton, a letter forwarding orchids from Robert H. Schomburgk, a letter from George Biddell Airy on a magnetic disturbance on an iron ship, a letter from John Taylor Coleridge conveying family news, and an envelope addressed in 1871 by one of the last survivors of Waterloo.
Miscellaneous items include broadsides from the Sierra Leone Turf Club and one regarding a regatta, and an invitation to the coronation of William IV.
Arrangement
The letters were originally in a bound volume, grouped roughly by type of material and by correspondent but otherwise in no discernible order. The original arrangement has been maintained.
Contents List
- Letter, Henry John Temple Palmerston to Henry William Macaulay 1831 Oct 25, 2 p. ALS
  Refers to letter of the 17th to Macaulay by Sir George Shee and the submission of Macaulay's name for the vacant Situation of His Majesty's Commissioner of Arbitration at Sierra Leone. Informs Macaulay that His Majesty's government requires abstaining from any commercial pursuits while holding Office in the Mixed Commission due to the incompatibility of the positions of Merchant and Commissioner of Arbitration.
- Appointment by King William IV 1835 Feb 25, 4 p. ADS
  Appointment declaring Henry William Macaulay as Commissary Judge and Walter William Lewis as Commissioner of Arbitration pursuant to a treaty with Spain for the abolition of the slave trade concluded 1817 Sep 23. Macaulay and Lewis' work is to be performed as a mixed commission with the Commissary Judge and Commissioner of Arbitration appointed by Spain, among others. Signed by Arthur Wellesley, Duke of Wellington, as Foreign Secretary.
- Appointment by King William IV 1835 Feb 25, 6 p. ADS
  Appointment declaring Henry William Macaulay as Commissary Judge and Walter William Lewis as Commissioner of Arbitration pursuant to a convention with Brazil on the abolition of the slave trade concluded 1826 Nov 23. This convention adopted several articles and provisions of the treaties made by King George III with the King of Portugal on 1815 Jan 22 and 1817 Jul 28. Macaulay and Lewis' work is to be performed as a mixed commission with the Commissary Judge and Commissioner of Arbitration appointed by Brazil, among others. Signed by Arthur Wellesley, Duke of Wellington, as Foreign Secretary.
- Appointment by King William IV 1835 Feb 25, 5 p. ADS
  Appointment Appointment declaring Henry William Macaulay as Commissary Judge and Walter William Lewis as Commissioner of Arbitration pursuant to a treaty with the Netherlands for the abolition of the slave trade concluded 1818 May 4. Macaulay and Lewis' work is to be performed as a mixed commission with the Commissary Judge and Commissioner of Arbitration appointed by each of the five nations participating. Signed by Arthur Wellesley, Duke of Wellington, as Foreign Secretary.
- Commission by Queen Victoria 1843 Sep 22, 5 p. ADS
  Commission declaring Henry William Macaulay as Commissioner and Charles Pettingal as Arbitrator pursuant to a treaty with Portugal concluded 1842 Jul 3. Macaulay and Pettingal's work is to be performed as a mixed commission with the Commissary Judge and Commissioner of Arbitration appointed by both nations. Signed by George Hamilton Gordon, Earl of Aberdeen.
- George Hamilton Gordon, Earl of Aberdeen to Her Majesty's Commissioners in Boa Vista 1845 Sep 30, 1 p. ALS
  Aberdeen writes to the Commissioners, enclosing a copy of correspondence relating to the Portuguese Government's intention of authorizing the Board of Superintendence of liberated Negroes at Boa Vista to distribute captured Negroes in any part of the Cape Verde Islands.
- Stratford Canning of Redcliffe to Her Majesty's Commissioners at Boa Vista 1845 Nov 27, 2 p. ALS
  Canning writes to the Commissioners, enclosing copies of correspondence with the Portuguese Government on the subject of the disposal of Negroes found on board of slave vessels captured by Portuguese Cruizers and condemned by the Mixed Court of which they are members. With enclosed obituary of Lord Shaftesbury.
- Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of Shaftesbury to Margaret Cropper 1852 Nov 23, 2 p. ALS
  Shaftesbury writes to Cropper regretting that he cannot adopt her previously proposed attitude towards immediate abolition. He proposes that admitting rather than denying the difficulties of immediate abolition will help abate hostility.
- Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of Shaftesbury to Margaret Cropper 1852 Nov 30, 4 p. ALS
  Shaftesbury writes to Cropper concerning two separate addresses circulating to be sent to London. He expresses joy over the activity in Liverpool in support of a universal goal. He suggests that Cropper and others in Liverpool continue to obtain signatures for their address while he and the London Committee do the same there. He explains that upon completion the two lists will be combined along with an explanation of differences in wording between the addresses and requests that Cropper not send anything to London until all lists can be combined in a "Single Cargo." Together with an undated [1888] newsclipping eulogy on the life of Lord Shaftesbury.
- Fragment, unsigned, relating to Henry William Macaulay's position as commissary judge. n.d., 1 p. AN
- Maria Maxfield to Henry William Macaulay 1834 Nov, 1 p. ALS
  Maxfield, Sierra Leone, requests the loan of half a dozen knives and forks and the use of some liquor on the occasion of her wedding the following day.
- George Freeman to Henry William Macaulay 1838 Feb 27, 1 p. ALS
  Freeman writes to Macaulay inquiring about any possible vacancies (vagence) in Macaulay's department and humbly requests consideration for any such positions
- Petition of John Samuel and related note 1838 Jan 5, 1 p. ALS
  Samuel petitions the successor of his master's estate for employment. He emphasizes his experience as a mason, but requests any available positions, including those of messenger or interpreter of Portuguese. A note at the bottom of the petition describes Samuel as a mason who arrived in Sierra Leone in Maxwell's time. Samuel was previously a steward on a slave ship that was taken by the Amelia frigate.
- John F. Spooler to William Wilberforce 1838 Apr 11, 2 p. ALS
  Spooler, Freetown, Sierra Leone, refers to a conversation with Mr. Cole in which he was informed to speak to Wilberforce regarding a possible position in a school for boys. He also requests any other position that it is in Wilberforce's power to give.
- James Carbinthy to Henry William Macaulay 1836 Sep 23, 2 p. ALS
  Carbinthy, London, informs Macaulay that his clothing consists of shoes, two shirts given to him by her Ladyship, and two pairs of stockings left to him by Macaulay. He explains that he is writing on the subject because he does not wish to trouble his captain about the matter, but that in general he is being well treated. He also explains that he wrote to his father about the matter but received no reply.
- Hannibal Marks to Captain Denman 1837 Apr 29, 1 p. ALS
  Marks, the gunner of the Scylla, writes to Captain Denman while a prisoner with the boat's crew in the hands of the Carlists. He ensures the captain that he was never treated better and that the captain that took him was very kind. He also describes a trip by Denman's orders that resulted in their capture.
- A. Marshall to Henry William Macaulay 1834 Nov, 2 p. ALS
  Marshall, Sierra Leone, apologizes to Macaulay that he is unable to come down as requested. He explains that his wound has not healed and that he is unable to stand upon it. He says that he will come once the wound is healed and begs for Macaulay's patience.
- Thomas Clarkson to "My Lord" 1841 Mar 17, 3 p. ALS
  Clarkson, Playford Hall near Ipswich, writes regarding the practice of slavery in America and his efforts to change opinion in the United States. He informs the recipient that the clergy of the South are not only slaveholders themselves and mistreat their slaves but that they defend the practice in the pulpit. He states that this defense of slavery has spread to the North and that overall, seven-tenths of the clergy in America do not consider slavery a sin. Clarkson was requested to use his influence to try and change the opinions of the clergy and, after deliberation due to his age, acquiesced. His writing on the subject was printed and sent to the United States, where 100,000 copies were to be made. [A letter to the clergy of various denominations, and to the slave-holding planters, in the southern parts of the United States of America] He sends a copy of his work to the recipient for review and to assess its likely effectiveness altering the clergy's position. Together with a newspaper clipping describing a memorial in memory of Clarkson.
- Frederick Douglass to Mrs. Edward Cropper 1858 Mar 8, 1 p. AL
  In a third person letter, Douglass, Rochester, N.Y., acknowledges Mrs. Cropper's letter dated January 8th and requests that the parcel for Mrs. Douglass be forwarded to Rochester, New York. Also expresses thanks to Mrs. Cropper for her past and continued interest and support of the abolitionist movement. Together with a newspaper clipping, 1907 October 4, from The Daily Telegraph, reviewing Booker T. Washington's biography of Douglass.
- Frederick Douglass to Mrs. E. Cropper 1859 May 27, 4 p. ALS
  Douglass, Rochester, N.Y., thanks Cropper for the Liverpool Antislavery Society donation towards the publication of his antislavery papers. He reports on the progress of the antislavery cause in the U.S. and the nature of the movement compared with ten years earlier. Specifically, he describes more action being taken by individuals than by organizations. He stresses the importance of constantly reminding the people about the movement in order to sway their opinions. He credits assistance from abroad with helping by allowing him to work more efficiently and by giving him influence among his people because he is not asking them for financial support. He also discusses the destitute situation of many slaves who have escaped to Canada and a plan to furnish escaping slaves with tools as they pass through.
- Broadsides: Sierra Leone Turf Club Races and a Regatta 1837 Dec 2, n.d., 2 broadsides
  Broadside setting the date for the Sierra Leone Turf Club races and outlining rules for riders, horses, schedule, as well as detailing prizes. Partial broadside of regulations for a regatta to be held Feb 7-9.
- Printed invitation from Hannah Cuthbert to Henry William Macaulay 1839 May 1, 1 p.
  Cuthbert, Freetown, Sierra Leone,invites Macaulay to luncheon at 3 o'clock in honor of the marriage of her daughter Miss N. Barnett to Mr. A. O'Conner.
- Printed funeral notice for Henry Fleet sent to Henry William Macaulay 1839 May 31, 1 p.
  The Wesleyan Missionaries Thomas Dove, Henry Badger and Thomas Edwards [Sierra Leone?] inform Mr. Macaulay of the death of the Reverend Henry Fleet. Funeral arrangements are outlined.
- Robert Cecil, Marquess of Salisbury, to Thomas Denman, Baron Denman 18?? Oct 5, 2 p. ALS
  Salisbury thanks Denman for the enclosure and hopes the unnamed task is not as formidable as people imagine.
- Robert Cecil, Marquess of Salisbury, to Thomas Denman, Baron Denman 1881 Mar 17, 3 p. ALS
  Salisbury thanks Denman for his letters. He states his belief that the Roman Catholics of Ireland could have been won over "for in other countries they do not usually take the side of insurrection, but fears that the opportunity has been lost for at least the present.
- Frank J. Mebbs to Margaret Cropper Feb 21, 4 p. ALS
  Mebbs, Kingston [Jamaica?], thanks Cropper for her letter. He tells her of how he has been busy in the office lately, and therefore has not gotten as much work done on his book as he would like. He states agreement with Cropper's opinion of Harry and concern for his future. He turns down Cropper's offer of payment for embroideries because of existing obligations to her, and offers to complete them free of charge. He refers to a loan expected from Mr. Cropper that was not received, and asks for any amount available to be sent.
- [ ? ] to Thomas Denman 1822 May 2, 2 p. ALS
  Promises to visit Denman's protégé in Pall Mall, but expresses hesitation about any assistance he can offer due to a lack of buyers. He expresses his desire to visit on the same day as Parr, because of his renewed vigor, but regrets that he is busy on that day, and therefore suggests that he will come on the 19th to celebrate Denman's election.
- William Wilberforce to Henry William Macaulay 182[?] Dec 24, 2 p. ALS
  Wilberforce, Uxbridge Common, informs Macaulay that he forwarded two letters to him that morning, but did not address them fully and tells Macaulay to inquire about them at the Post Office. Sends well wishes to the Cropper family. With newsclipping from The Daily News, 1907 June 10, regarding the sale of Battersea Rise House, Wilberforce's London home.
- Duke of Wellington to Major Wilson 1831 Aug 31, 2 p. ALS
  In a third person letter Wellington thanks Wilson for his letter of the 30th, promises to express an opinion on the Warrington and Newton Railroad as soon as evidence is printed, and asks that Wilson not take the trouble of calling on him.
- Alexander Fergusson, Joseph Chabinthy, and Thomas Williams to Henry William Macaulay 1835 Oct 22, 2 p. ALS
  Fergusson, Chabinthy and Williams, Freetown, Sierre Leone, ask Macaulay to baptize them because they were told it was a necessity and that having read the Bible is nothing without it. Letter is docketed "Specimen letter from the boys wishing to be baptized."
- George William Spencer, Duke of Devonshire, to Margaret Cropper 18[?]9 Sep 19, 1 p. AL
  Spencer invites Mr. and Mrs. Cropper to dinner and to stay at Lismore Castle. Signature cut away.
- J. Fowell Buxton to Thomas Denman 1841 Mar 18, 2 p. ALS
  Buxton, Brewery, Spitalsfields, congratulates Denman on his son's involvement in the "(I hope) fatal blow which has been struck at the Slave Trade on that part of the coast." He expresses joy that the achievement was done by the son of a "faithful friend of the Negro" when others had not been sympathetic to the cause.
- Thomas Babington Macaulay to Mrs. Henry Macaulay 18[48?] May 3, 2 p. ALS
  Macaulay thanks Mrs. Macaulay for the present of a chair that belonged to her late husband and a likeness of him.
- George William Spencer, Duke of Devonshire to Margaret Cropper 1856 Mar 13, 1 p. ALS
  Devonshire deeply regrets that he cannot comply with Cropper's request, and expresses his inability to do so.
- Thomas Babington Macaulay to Mrs. Henry William Macaulay 1848 May 1, 4 p. ALS
  Thomas Babington Macaulay to Mrs. Henry William Macaulay Macaulay thanks his sister-in-law for her promise of an engraving as a memorial to his brother. He mentions that he did not see Macaulay's children's picture at the Exhibition of the Royal Academy as he had expected. He also sends his love to Selina
- Benjamin Collins Brodie to Margaret Cropper 1855 Aug 14, 2 p. ALS
  Brodie informs Cropper that the place was not sold, but bought in at L27000. He explains the difficulty of selling on account and promises to update her if he hears anything more. Also invites the Croppers to look at the property at Broome.
- Frederick Douglass to Margaret Cropper 1858 Sep 3, 1 p. ALS
  Douglass thanks Cropper for her previously sent gifts which had only reached Douglass a few days prior. Cropper sent a scarf to Mrs. Douglass and a volume of Dr. Livingston's Travels in Africa to Douglass. Douglass expresses gratitude for Cropper's interest in the cause, and also mentions that he is writing on the anniversary of his escape from slavery
- Henry William Macaulay to Margaret Cropper 1838 Sep 15, 2 p. ALS
  Macaulay thanks Cropper for her kindness towards his sister Selina and for her letter of the 29th of August and one dictated by Selina. He wishes to inquire further about one passage of her letter.
- George William Spencer, Duke of Devonshire to Margaret Cropper [?] Oct 3, 2 p. ALS
  Devonshire apologizes for his late reply to Cropper's letter in favor of an unnamed workman. Promises that upon his return to Chatsworth he will take some green from a now locked cupboard and send them on to the workman, provided that he is given a name and address.
- Catherine Marsh to Margaret Cropper [?] May 19, 4 p. ALS
  Marsh thanks Cropper for her invitation, but declines because she is busy until she leaves for Scotland. Also encloses a speech in case Cropper has not read it already.
- H. C. Hamilton to Henry William Macaulay n.d., 2 p. ALS
  Hamilton, Congotown, requests that Macaulay give him any available position on one of Her Majesty's ships.
- Invitation [1830], 1 item
  Printed invitation to The Coronation of Their Most Sacred Majesties made out to His Majesty's Attorney General. Entry at the West Door.
- Hugh Charles Clifford to Margaret Cropper n.d., 1 p. ALS
  Clifford hopes to be able to dine with Cropper on Friday the 13th if nothing comes up in the House of Lords to detain him.
- J[ohn?] MacGregor to "Dear Madam" Wednesday, 2 p. ALS
  MacGregor accepts an invitation to dinner on Friday.
- [Thomas Babington Macaulay] to Margaret Cropper 1853 Aug 24, 2 p. ALS
  Partial Partial letter to Cropper inquiring about papers in a collection. Asks about Lord _____'s M.S.S. as well as any documents pertaining to 1689, 1690 and 1691, probably for his book on "The history of England from the accession of James II." Mentions that letters relating to Lord Cromwell's time are not of much use.
- Envelopes to Margaret Cropper [?] May 13 and n.d., 2 items
  Partial envelopes addressed to Margaret Cropper
- George Biddell Airy to Charles Parker 1838 Oct 28, 1 p. ALS
  Biddell is in Liverpool and will attempt to call on Parker as soon as he is able. Mentions that the purpose of his visit is to examine an iron ship belonging to W. Cairns to try and correct a magnetic disturbance. Also notes that he saw Dr. and Mrs. [Thomas Stewart?] Traill and their daughter at Greenwich.
- George William Spencer, Duke of Devonshire, to Margaret Cropper [?] Apr 30, 1 p. ALS
  Devonshire reports that he has been sick with bronchitis for over a week and is unable to assist.
- Henry William Macaulay to Margaret Cropper 1855 Aug 16, 2 p. ALS
  Macaulay reports finding her letter among other papers with its seal unbroken. He attempts to ease her worries over a young man who is not an energetic worker, but mentions that the problem should be corrected. He also sends his love to Edward and the children.
- Beaconsfield [Benjamin Disraeli] to Miss [?] [?] Jul 1, 3 p. ALS
  Beaconsfield thanks his correspondent for a gift [of grapes?] and invites her to call any time after five.
- Richard Wellesley to The Lord Chief Justice [Thomas Denman] 1840 Nov 22, 1 p. ALS
  Wellesley confirms his Lordship and the Provost of Eton's visit at 3 o'clock that day. He also reports that his health is much improved and that his doctors promise him a "new Lease on Life."
- Sir John Taylor Coleridge to Thomas Denman 1849 Aug 6, 4 p. ALS
  Coleridge inquires about Denman, and asks to be sent news from someone other than Denman himself. He discusses Denman's giving up his work as a judge, and the effect his workload may have had upon his health. Discusses his future son-in-law and preparations for the wedding. Reports on his latest circuit and on winning a shilling on a point in the Highway Act. Includes a passage in Greek. Also mentions that Lady Coleridge sends kind regards to Lady Denman.
- [John?] Russell, Lord Russell to "My Dear Lord" [Thomas Denman] 1841 Mar 11, 2 p. ALS
  Russell congratulates Denman on the conduct of his son on the Coast of Africa and discusses the effect of Joseph Denman's actions on the African chiefs and the slave trade in the Gallinas.
- Envelope and fragment to Major Wilson at the United Service Club n.d., 2 items
- [?] to "My Dear Sir" 1841 Oct 27, 2 p. ALS
  Correspondent notes that an order in Council is about to be opened upon the subject of slavery. It is necessary that the recipient take some action [publication?] so the order can proceed without delay.
- Edward Robert Bulwer Lytton to Lord Denman 1884 Nov 6, 1 p. ALS
  Earl and Lady Lytton thank Denman for his congratulations.
- Envelope addressed to "The Lord Denman" 1871, 1 item
  Pencil note on envelope reads "From Captain [?] one of the few survivors of Waterloo--Peninsular War 1871"
- Robert H. Schomburgk to Charles Parker 1839 Jun 1, 1 p. ALS
  Schomburgk forwards Forwards a box of plants for his Grace the Duke of Bedford after returning from the Interior. Apologizes for giving Parker the trouble of receiving and forwarding packages, and explains that Sir William Hooker instructed him to do so. Also asks that the box be forwarded as soon as possible because it contains orchids.
- William Wilberforce to R.H. Davis 18[20?] Nov 27, 3 p. ALS
  Wilberforce Informs Davis that Lord Calthorpe is coming to visit Wilberforce and may arrive the next night on his way to Warwicke. Explains that they may go together to Blaise Castle and asks if he may show Davis' "horrid statement" to Calthorpe. He stresses that Calthorpe is highly principled and may be relied upon for secrecy, but Wilberforce requires Davis' permission before sharing the information. Wilberforce discusses the lack of feeling and principle evident in the conduct attributed to the Queen. During his writing, Wilberforce was called away and he hurriedly signs the letter.
- Duke of Wellington to Major Wilson 18[?] Dec 2, 2 p. AL
  In a third person letter Wellington thanks Wilson, but informs him that he must decline to interfere with the proposed bill for making a railway from Warrington to Liverpool.
- Envelope addressed to Margaret Cropper 1860 May 19, 1 item